<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The old vvaye A sermon preached at Oxford, the eight day of Iuly, being the Act Sunday. 1610. By Robert Abbott ...</title>
            <author>Abbot, Robert, 1560-1618.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 102 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 53</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100540</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836377</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836377</idno>
            <idno type="VID">645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18831)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 864:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The old vvaye A sermon preached at Oxford, the eight day of Iuly, being the Act Sunday. 1610. By Robert Abbott ...</title>
                  <author>Abbot, Robert, 1560-1618.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 59, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Stansby] for Eleazar Edgar, and Ambrose Garbrand, and are to bee solde at their shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the signe of the Wind-mill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:645:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE OLD WAYE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A</hi> SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT OXFORD, The eight day of Iuly, being the Act Sunday. 1610.</p>
            <p>By ROBERT ABBOTT, Doctor of Diuinitie, and Maiſter of Balioll COLLEDGE.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Eleazar Edgar,</hi> and <hi>Ambroſe Carbrand,</hi> and are to bee ſolde at their Shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the Signe of the Wind-mill. 1610.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:645:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:645:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VEREND FATHER IN God, the Lord Archbiſhop of CANTER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BVRIE his Grace, Primate and Metropolitane of all ENGLAND, Chauncelour of the Vniuerſitie of OXFORD, one of his Maieſties moſt Honourable Priuie Counſell, my verie good LORD.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſt Reuerend Father, albeit it be ſomewhat beſide cuſtom to make Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sermons, yet it is not beſide dutie in me to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb facs="tcp:645:3"/> to your Grace, the firſt fruits of my returne to this famous Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, wherof the chiefeſt protection vnder his moſt Excellent Maieſtre, belongeth to your Grace, &amp; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in through your Grace his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, though to a forward and wel-willing companie, I am now become a Head, where I liued ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times an inferior member. Which place, as by your Grace his fauour it hath befallen mee, without my expectation or ſeeking, ſo I deſire to vſe it being befallen mee in ſuch ſort, as to ſatisfie your Grace his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation and good conceipt of me. In the entrance whereof, if I haue done a ſeruice ſo acceptable and ſo likly to profit many; as the deſire of many for the publiſhing of this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb facs="tcp:645:3"/> would import, it ſhal (I hope) ominate further good in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of my abode here, which I wiſh to be no longer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhalbe for the glorie of God, the ſeruice of his Maieſty, &amp; the benefit both in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall and in generall of the Church of God. To which I ſhall bee the more encouraged, if it ſhall pleaſe your Grace to accept in good part, this ſmall worke as a token of my thankefull minde, which in all due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I recommend to your Grace his fauour, and your ſelfe in all your affaires, to the mercie and bleſsing of Almightie GOD, who euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more ſo aſsiſt &amp; guide you in your Paſtoral care and Gouernement of his CHVRCH, as that when the chiefe Paſtour ſhall appeare, you
<pb facs="tcp:645:4"/> may in lieu of preſent toyle and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, receiue an incorruptible Crowne of glorie in that life that is for euer. So reſting,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Graces in all most humble affection and duetie, R. ABBOTT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:645:4"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Hristian Reader, lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle thought I when I Preached this Sermon to take a ſecond paines about it to write it to the Preſſe, but the earneſt requeſt of diuers perſons hath preuailed with me, to remember them that heard me of that they heard, and to impart the ſame to many others that heard me not. If there may be to thee that good there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which they haue hoped for, that haue ſo earneſtly deſired it, I ſhall bee glad that God diſpoſed me to the ſeruice of that day. Of the matter here intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:645:5"/> I know much might haue bene ſaid, but I was to keepe my ſelfe within the compaſſe of a Sermon, and very little haue I now ſet downe either more or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then I then ſpake. Let mee now, good Reader, vſe this opportunity to requeſt pardon of thee, if by ſuch oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions which haue ſundrie wayes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallen me, ſince the Printing of my laſt Booke, I be ſomewhat the longer, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I giue thee the anſwere to Doctor <hi>Biſhops</hi> late reproofe. I haue in the end of that laſt Booke, giuen thee an aduertiſement, which the Printer on the toppe of euery Page, giuing to that Addition the Title of the whole worke going before, hath miſ named, <hi>The third part of the defence of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Catholicke,</hi> by which thou maiest take knowledge of the qualitie
<pb facs="tcp:645:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> and condition of that reproofe. I pray thee let that ſatisfie thee for the time, till leiſure may ſerue to goe forward with that, which I haue already in good part begunne. Albeit by the reading of that Aduertiſement, thou maieſt happily conceiue, that it is but labour ill beſtowed, to deale with a man ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely impudent, as thou maiest per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue <hi>Doct. Biſhop</hi> hath in that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe framed himſelfe to bee. But whatſoeuer his booke be in it ſelfe, thou ſhalt ſee it will giue mee occaſion of a worke, which I hope ſhall giue ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and be helpfull vnto many, God therein aſsiſting me, by thy prayer for me, and giuing me health and ſtrength for the performance of it. Further I cannot omit, to wiſh thee in my ſecond part against the ſaid <hi>Doct. Biſhop,</hi> to take notice of one ſpeciall fault ſince
<pb facs="tcp:645:6"/> eſpied by me, and not noted in the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, which are there ſet downe in the end. <hi>Pag. 978.</hi> in the laſt line thou readeſt, <hi>He receiued of them no warrant of authority, but only by conſent,</hi> where it ſhould be, <hi>but only teſtimony of conſent.</hi> Some other faults there were ouerſlipped in my ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie reading, as <hi>pag. 362. line 2. This ſpirit and prayer a true witneſſe,</hi> for <hi>this ſpirit of payer is a true witneſſe,</hi> and <hi>pag. 967. lin. 9. it is vnknowne,</hi> for, <hi>it is not vnknowne,</hi> which and ſuch like thou canſt by thine owne vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding eaſily diſcerne. For con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, vnderſtand I pray thee, that ſome man lighting vpon my copie of that booke, after it was paſt my hands plaied the Cuckow with me, and laied ſome egges of his in my neſt. As <hi>pag. 549. lin. 27.</hi> where I had ſaied, <hi>M.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:645:6"/> Biſhop <hi>according to his ignorance,</hi> he made it, <hi>M.</hi> Biſhop <hi>according to his opinion muffled in the miſts of ignorance.</hi> Likewiſe <hi>pag. 762. l. 38.</hi> where I had ſaid, <hi>theſe are the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of the fornications of the whoore of Babylon, things reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, witleſſe, ſenſeleſſe, meere wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheries and inchauntments of mens mindes,</hi> he hath added, <hi>and the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely fruits of a barren ſtrumpet.</hi> Theſe two I noted obſcurely before, though I did not ſignifie by what means they came in, which now I thought good to doe. Another edition, if neede be, and God ſo will, ſhall expunge theſe and the reſt of theſe ſlouens blots; in the meane time, I pray thee, paſſe them ouer, if thou finde any more of the ſame kinde.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:645:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:645:7"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT OXFORD, The eight of Iuly, 1610.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>IEREM. 6. 16.</bibl>
               <q>Thus ſaith the Lord, ſtand vpon the wayes, and behold and aske for the old way, which is the good way, and walke therein, and yee ſhall find reſt for your Soules.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a memorable ſentence, and worthy alwayes to bee regarded, which our Sauiour Chriſt the chiefe Maſter of ſentences hath dictated for a perpetuall caueat vnto vs; <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 16. 26.</note> 
               <hi>VVhat ſhall it profit a man, though hee winne the whole world, if hee looſe his owne ſoule? The loſse of the ſoule,</hi> what is it but the loſſe of the reſt of the ſoule, whereby it periſheth,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:645:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Grego. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. lib. 4. cap. 7. <hi>Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter pertre di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus vt non ſit, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ter perire di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimus et male ſit. &amp;c. Humana anima beate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere ſiue per vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m ſiue per ſupplicium per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, eſſentialiter viuere non a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Not ſo as not to be,</hi> as <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>but ſo as to be in euill,</hi> and looſeth, <hi>not the life of eſſence and being, but the life of bliſſe and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> whileſt being diuided from God, in whom onely is the fountaine of life and bliſſe, it liueth immortally in death, and in a miſerable end findeth no end of miſerie, and is vncapable of any deſtruction where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bee freed from deſtruction: Now if the gaine of the whole world be but loſſe and dammage, when it is ioyned with this loſſe of Soule, how highly, how deepely doeth it concerne vs amidſt our vſing the world and the things of the world, to haue alwayes an eye to our Soules health, and to be alwayes iealous of ſo intricating our ſelues in the troubles and buſineſſes of the world, as to runne in danger of excluding our Soules from reſt with God? As touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the meanes of finding this reſt, the Prophet in the words which I haue here propounded, very notably inſtructeth vs,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Yee ſhall find reſt for your Soules. 2. Vpon the wayes.</hi>
               </note> 1. Commending it as the finall ende of all our trauaile, by this meanes onely and not otherwiſe to be found; 2. Noting the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:645:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> of finding it, by reaſon of ſo many counterfeit wayes pretended to bring vs to it, when indeede they leade vs from it. 3. Shewing vs from whom we are to take<note place="margin">3. Thus ſaith the Lord.</note> the certaine direction of the right way. 4. Declaring what that direction is, both<note place="margin">4. Stand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, aske.</note> as touching the care that wee are to vſe for the finding of that way, and 5. As tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching<note place="margin">5. The olde way, which is the good way. 6. And walke therein.</note> the marke whereby it is to be know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en. 6. Inſtructing vs what our duetie is when wee haue receiued the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the way, euen <hi>to walke therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As touching the firſt (which I make the firſt for my order of handling, though in place of words it be the laſt) what is all the life that we liue here, but temptation and warfare and trouble? What other then a reſtleſſe <hi>Euripus,</hi> ſtill ebbing and flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; continually toſſed too and fro, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracted with cares, perplexed with feares, oppreſſed with ſorrowes, yeelding no Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie without ſome Gall, no calme that is not intercepted or interrupted with ſome ſtorme. <note n="c" place="margin">Ouid.</note> 
               <hi>Nulla eſt ſyncera voluptas,</hi> ſaith the Poet; <hi>There is no pleaſure that is not blended
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:645:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> with ſomewhat that is diſtaſtfull and vnplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Eccleſ. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>I haue conſidered,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon, all the workes that are done vnder the Sunne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all is vanitie and vexation of ſpirit.</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Grego. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. l. 23. c. 15. <hi>Via eſt vita prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſens qua ad pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam tendimus, &amp; idcirco hic occulto dei iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio frequenti perturbatione conterimur ne viam pro patria diligamus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This life,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorie, is the way for vs to goe to our Countrey, and therfore by Gods ſecret iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, we are here beaten and broken with often trouble, that we may not in ſteede of our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey fall in loue with the way.</hi> But yet againſt all this vanitie and mutabilitie and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, vaine man is euermore labouring to ſettle vnto himſelfe an eſtate, wherein to enioy contentment, and peace, and reſt; which hee ſeeketh here and ſeeketh there, but findeth it no where; and thinketh to gaine it by obteining this deſire, and this failing, by obtaining that, but no whit the neerer, either by this or that, whileſt in the hauing of things, hee findeth not that reſt which hee promiſed to himſelfe in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of them, and therefore hauing obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his deſire againe and againe, yet is ſtill ready to deſire againe; euen as the Dropſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſeaſed man drinketh to aſwage his thirſt, and by and by his Soule is drie, and hee is
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:645:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> deſirous to drinke againe. For as in the great deluge of the world, the Doue which <hi>Noah</hi> ſent firſt out of the Arke, <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 8. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Found no reſt for the ſole of her foote, vntill ſhee returned vnto the Arke againe,</hi> Euen ſo the Soule of man being in ſinne, gone out from God, and flying too and fro in the deluge of the miſeries of humane life, findeth no where to reſt it ſelfe, vntil it take courſe to returne to God againe; God hauing engrauen it vpon all the creatures of the world, which he ſaid of old to the Iewes concerning Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, <note n="g" place="margin">Micah. 2. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Non eſt haec requies veſtra; This is not your reſt,</hi> So as that they repell and put backe from them our deſires and delights, and ſuffer vs not with continuance to ſticke vpon them, by reaſon that in the vſe, they breede a wearineſſe and lothing of them, and <note n="h" place="margin">Tertul. de habit. mulier. <hi>ſemper abundan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia contumelioſa in ſemetipſameſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Abundance,</hi> as <hi>Tertullian</hi> ſaith, <hi>cauſeth alwayes it owne contumely and diſgrace.</hi> There is nothing ſo ſightly as that the eye ioyeth continually to ſee it; no melodie ſo ſweete but that ſtill to heare it, rather dulleth then delighteth; nothing ſo pleaſing to the taſte, but that continuall ſacietie and fulneſſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:645:10"/> maketh it lothſome and vnpleaſing; ſo as that <note n="i" place="margin">Greg. Moral. lib. 26. cap. 28. <hi>Per multa duci tur vt quia qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate rerum non poteſt, ſaltem va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietate ſatictur.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>varietie of things,</hi> as <hi>Gregorie</hi> well obſerueth, we are forced to ſeeke that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment which we cannot find in <hi>the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of them.</hi> It remaineth therefore that there is no true reſt but in the enioying of God, nothing being able to content the Soule but he that created the Soule, nor to ſatisfie the deſire of the heart, but hee that made the heart to deſire him. In him is riches, and beautie, &amp; glorie, and ſtrength, and immortalitie, and whatſoeuer apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the bliſſe and happineſſe either of body or Soule; ſo as that hauing obtei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him, there is nothing further for vs to deſire or wiſh for. The little ſight and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling that we haue of the grace of God how great peace doth it adminiſter vnto vs, euen in this life; euen <note n="k" place="margin">Phil. 4. 7.</note> 
               <hi>the peace of God which paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth all vnderſtanding?</hi> How hath it fortified the hearts of Gods Saints, to goe with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy &amp; cheerfulnes, <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 66. 12.</note> 
               <hi>through fire and water,</hi> againſt all the iniuries and violences of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe &amp; euil men; perſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, baniſhment, impriſonment, hunger, cold, nakednes, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:645:10"/> death it ſelfe, the inner man reioycing and reſting in God, when the outward man hath beene toſſed too and fro, with the ſtormes and tempeſts of the world, and <note n="m" place="margin">Cyprian. de Mortalit. <hi>Inter ruinas humani generis ſtare e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>amidſt the ruines of mankind ſtanding vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſpeaketh, looking with boldneſſe vp to heauen, as expecting re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption and deliuerance to bee yeelded vnto them from thence? Now if there bee ſo much in the ſhadow, what ſhall there be in the ſubſtance, where there ſhall bee nothing to interrupt our glorious reſt, where we ſhall <note n="n" place="margin">1. Cor. 13. 12.</note> 
               <hi>ſee face to face, and know euen as we are knowen,</hi> where <note n="o" place="margin">Apoc. 7. 16. 17. &amp; 21. 4.</note> 
               <hi>there ſhall be no more death nor hunger, nor thirſt, nor crying, nor paine but God ſhall wipe away all teares from our eyes,</hi> where it ſhall finally &amp; fully be accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed which the Prophet hath ſaid of <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed of the Lord,</hi> 
               <note n="p" place="margin">Eſa. 35. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Euerlaſting ioy ſhall bee vpon their heads, they ſhall obtaine ioy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſorrow and mourning ſhall flie away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3 But a matter it is of no great diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie, to conceiue that all our true content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reſt ſtandeth in GOD, and in the fruition of his goodneſſe, the greater
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:645:11"/> doubt and queſtion, is concerning the way to come to God. Wherein the wit of man hath infinitely buſied it ſelfe, who appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending this principle, that by Religion and ſeruice of God, wee are to come to God, hath thought himſelfe wiſe enough, to direct what is fit for God, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend that light that ſhould giue him conduct and guidance into the preſence of God. Now it being with men according to the prouerbe, <hi>Quot homines, tot ſententiae, So many men, ſo many minds,</hi> it hath by this meanes come to paſſe, that varietie of wits hath ſhewed it ſelfe in this behalfe by va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of deuiſes, whence haue growen both without the Church, and within the Church ſo many opinions of God, ſo great differences of Religion, ſo many Sects, and Schiſmes, and Hereſies, as in all ages we haue ſeene, euery of them preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it ſelfe to be the right way, and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſelfe with colours and ſhewes of trueth, and promiſing the reſt and peace of God and all happineſſe from him. And indeede if the diuell ſhould appeare and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:645:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhew himſelfe in his owne likeneſſe, and ſhould profeſſe himſelfe a deceiuer and a deſtroyer, euery man would abhorre him and flie from him, but therefore he dealeth<note place="margin">pſal. 39. 11.</note> like the Moth, <note n="q" place="margin">Greg. Moral. lib. 5. cap. 29. <hi>Tinea damnam facil &amp; ſonitum non facit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>VVhich doeth the harme,</hi> as <hi>Gregorie</hi> ſaith, <hi>and maketh no noyſe or ſound of it.</hi> Yea <note n="r" place="margin">2. Cor. 11. 14.</note> 
               <hi>he transformeth himſelfe into an Angell of light,</hi> and teacheth his Agents and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>to transforme themſelues as if they were the miniſters of righteouſneſſe,</hi> to write <hi>Pharmaca, medicines,</hi> where they ſhould write <hi>Venena, poyſons,</hi> and to Suger the brims of their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toxicated Cups, that men the more greedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and without ſuſpicion may drinke thoſe venimous potions, which they miniſter vnto them therein. Thus euen <hi>Celſus</hi> the Philoſopher vpon his defenſes of Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme, ſetteth an inſcription of <note n="ſ" place="margin">Origen. cont. Celſum. lib. 1. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>era oratio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the word of trueth. Manicheus</hi> that blaſphemous Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke, taking in hand to write to the Church his da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable paradoxes, doubteth not to begin thus, <note n="t" place="margin">Auguſt cont. Epiſt Fundam. c. 5. <hi>Maniche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us Apoſtolus Ieſu Chriſti, &amp;c Haec ſut ſalubria ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba de perenni ac v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uo fonte.</hi>
               </note> Manicheus <hi>the Apoſtle of Ieſus Chriſt: theſe are the wholeſome words which iſſue out of the euerlaſting &amp; liuing foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine. Chryſoſtome</hi> reporteth of the Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:645:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Heretickes, That <note n="u" place="margin">Chryſoſt. de ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct. &amp; ador<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emper di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nt, <hi>No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cia <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they were alwayes ſaying; VVe walke in the right faith.</hi> Yea, <note n="x" place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. 56. <hi>Nullus error ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ud<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t extollere ad congregandas ſibi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urbas impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>torum qui non Chriſtian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> conquirat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>all Hereſies,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſomewhere noteth, <hi>Doe ſeeke the cloke and couerture of the name of Chriſt,</hi> and euery one ſaith of his owne ſect; <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Idem</hi> cont. Fauſt. l. 13. c. 15. <hi>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t, Salus qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chriſtus promiſit apud me eſt, ego dabo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The ſaluation which Chriſt hath promiſed is with me, I will giue it.</hi> By reaſon whereof it commeth to paſſe, which <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of Rome ſaith, That <note n="z" place="margin">Leo in Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit. Dom. ſer. 5. <hi>Nonin ſolo opere virtutum aut in ſola obſeruantia mandatorum ſed etiam in tramite fidei anguſta &amp; ardua eſt viaquae ducit ad vitam &amp; magni laboris eſt magni<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> inter du <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias imperitorum op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>iones &amp; veri ſimiles ſalſitales <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nam ſanae do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ſemita in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſis greſsibus ambulare, &amp; cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vndi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſe laquei erroreſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> oppo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at omne per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ulum deceptionis cua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not onely in the worke of vertue, and keeping the commandements of God, but alſo as touching the way and path of right faith, ſtrait and narrow is the way that leadeth vnto life, and a matter of great labour and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger it is, amidst the doubtfull opinions of vnskil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full men and their colourable falſhoods, to walke the one path of ſound doctrin without ſtumbling or offence, and where on euery ſide there lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs ſnares of errors yet to eſcape all danger of ſuch deceipt.</hi> Now many there are who hearing this multiplicitie of wayes, are of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended hereat, and becauſe it is a queſtion which is the right way, therefore ſit them downe and go no way at all, or goe onely the way that companie &amp; occaſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto them, being ready to leaue it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:645:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> when occaſion moueth them other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. But farre be it from any of vs to bee of this mind; Yea rather as the wayfaring man in his iourney, hearing of the perplex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>itie of the way, and that there are many by-pathes and turnings by which hee may goe amiſſe, doeth not therefore giue ouer his iourney, or goe on at all aduenture, but is rather the more earneſt and carefull to enquire and learne the way; euen ſo are we in this caſe to deale, that the malice of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan purpoſely labouring to breede doubt and difficultie of the way of life, doe not aſtoniſh vs, or driue vs to neglect of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and faith towards God, but rather ſtirre vp and ſharpen our induſtrie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our to ſearch and trie which is the true faith. And if as touching the things of this preſent life, we haue care to gaine the skill and knowledge to diſcerne money, whether it bee current and lawfull, and wares whether they be Marchantable and true, and meate whether it bee wholeſome and ſound; much more may wee thinke it concerneth vs, to learne the skill &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:645:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> of true Religion, and to gaine abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to diſcerne and iudge of erronious and falſe worſhippes, wherein is a departure from God, and the making of the way to our owne deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="4">4 And the more doth it concerne vs to be warie in this behalfe, for that amongſt thoſe many wayes, which wee ſee diuerſly frequented by diuers men, there is but one onely way that leadeth vnto God. As there<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ephe. 4. 4, 5, 6</note> is but <hi>one God</hi> who hath called vs, and <hi>one Lord,, Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> by whom we are called, and <hi>one heauen</hi> whereto we are called, ſo al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo there is but <hi>one faith</hi> to know God in Ieſus Chriſt, to obtaine life and ſaluation in heauen by him. <note n="a" place="margin">Hilar. de Trinit. lib. 11. <hi>Quis ambiget extra fidem eſſe quicquid extra fidem vnam eſt?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>It is without the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſse of faith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hilarie, whatſoeuer is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the compaſse of one faith,</hi> and <hi>Leo,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Leo in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiu dom. Ser. 4. <hi>Niſivna eſt, fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des non eſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Except it be one onely, it is no faith.</hi> Abſurdly therefore doe they erre and are deceiued, who with <note n="c" place="margin">Socrat. hiſt. lib. 4. c. 27. <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtius admone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat deum velle tam diuerſa ac dispari opinio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num ratione glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam ſuam illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrare.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Themiſtius</hi> the Philoſopher amongſt the Pagans, or with <hi>Rhetorious</hi> the Hereticke amongſt Chriſtians, doe thinke that <hi>God liketh well of the varietie of Religions,</hi> and <note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. de haereſ. cap. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>A Rhetorio hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſis exorta quae omnes haereticos recte ambulare &amp; vera dicere affirmat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>that all Heretickes walke aright and ſpeake
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:645:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> truth;</hi> ſo that it skilleth not of what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion a man be, if he be of any; as if heauen were a common harbour for all profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to arriue at, a common Inne to giue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainement to all that will offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto it: but ſo certaine a thing it is, that there is but onely one truth, one onely true religion, as that euery ſect and ſchiſme and hereſie profeſſeth it ſelfe only to be the truth, as graunting it out of common in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct to be a thing to be preſumed, that it cannot be the truth, except it only be the truth.</p>
            <p n="5">5 Now which that only true way is, and how it is to be knowen, none can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter teach vs then God himſelfe to whom we goe. For as <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 11.</note> no man knoweth the things of man, but the ſpirit of man which is in him (which yet knoweth not it ſelfe) ſo no man knoweth the things of God but the ſpirit of God, and he <note n="f" place="margin">Ver. 10.</note> 
               <hi>to whom they are reuealed by the ſame ſpirit.</hi> And as no man ſeeth the Sunne but by the light of the Sunne it ſelfe, ſo doth no man ſee or know God, but by thoſe reſplendent beames of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:645:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> light which iſſue from him in his holy word, whereby he vouchſafeth to mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter vnto vs the vnderſtanding of his waies. And therefore very well S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaith, <note n="g" place="margin">Ambroſ. Ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Coeli myſter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> not eat me Deus ipſequi condid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, non homo qui ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ipſum ignorauit. Cai magis de Deo quam Deo cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let God himſelfe that made heauen, teach me the myſtery of heauen, not man who had not vnderstanding to know himſelfe. Whom ſhall I beleeue concerning God, rather then God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi> 
               <note n="h" place="margin">Oroſ. hiſt. lib. 6. cap. 1. <hi>Ab ipſo audias, ipſi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Deo credas quod verum ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis ſcire de Deo.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Heare of God himſelfe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Oroſius, and beleeue God himſelfe as touching that truth which thou wouldeſt know concerning GOD.</hi> Therefore the Prophet here being to giue inſtruction concerning the way to come to God, and to finde reſt with him, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth nothing of himſelfe, but deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his leſſon from the Lord, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> And this is the onely certaine direction of true faith, and of the worſhip of God. It ſtandeth not in the dictates of men, nor in the definitions of Councels, nor in the reuelations of Angels, but the finall reſolution of all Controuerſies of Religion muſt be into this iſſue, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Auguſt. Ep. 48. <hi>Audi, Dicit Dominus; non, dicit Donat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, aut Rogatus, aut <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>incentius, aut Hilarius, aut Auguſtinus, ſed dicit Deminus</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Heare, thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin:</hi> not, <hi>thus ſaith</hi> Donatus, <hi>or</hi> Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatus,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:645:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>or</hi> Vincentius, <hi>or</hi> Hilary, <hi>or</hi> Auſtin, but, <hi>thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> This onely is it that can truely ſtabliſh the conſcience of man. Other things may breede maze and aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and may draw the benummed fancy to the following of this, or that; but the true life and ſenſe of Religion ariſeth only from this ground, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> Which notwithſtanding to the Papiſts is an importable yoake, who haue tranſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the authority of Religion to mortall men, to Doctors, and Fathers, and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, and crie the names of theſe aloud, but cannot endure to be required for proofe of their doctrine, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord.</hi> Albeit neyther do they pleade thoſe names as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that their Religion can ſtand ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Fathers or Councels, but onely to withdraw their followers from the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and due regard of, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord;</hi> that hauing once pulled them from thence, they may the more eaſily bring them by degrees to themſelues and their Church, to the decrees &amp; decretals of their Popes and Biſhops, to tye their opinion and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:645:15"/> of Religion wholly vpon them. Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> when for the proofe of their ſeuen Sacraments he could bring no wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> eyther of Councels or Fathers for more then 12. hundred years after Chriſt, bringing at laſt for proof therof the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Trent, to make good this proofe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with one breath bloweth the other all away. <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Contra Papae autoritat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Auguſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us, nec Hicronymus nec aliquis Docto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuam ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentia d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>fendit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The validity &amp; force,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of all the ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Councels, and of all doctrines of faith depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth of the authority of the Church that now is.</hi> Let the Fathers all ſay what they wil, what is that to the purpoſe? It is the Church now in being (wee know what Church they mean) that muſt ſtrike the ſtroake in all. Accordingly is it written in the Gloſſe of their Canon law. <hi rend="sup">k</hi> 
               <hi>neither</hi> Auſtin, <hi>nor</hi> Ierom <hi>nor any of the Doctors may maintain his opinion againſt the authority of the Pope:</hi> And in the law it ſelfe, <note n="l" place="margin">Diſt. 19. Si Romanorum. <hi>Romanorum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ficum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creto caeteror<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m opuſcula tract<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>orum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ppr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vel repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The workes of other writers are allowed or reiected according to the Popes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree.</hi> Yea further, they haue thus whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red one to another in their <hi>Index Expurga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torius,</hi> though not thinking that we ſhould heare them; <note n="m" place="margin">Index Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>In the olde Catholicke Writers
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:645:15"/> we beare with very many errours, we extenuate them, we excuſe them, by ſome deuiſed ſhift we denie them, or faine ſome conuenient meaning of them when they are oppoſed to vs in diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or in contentions, or controuerſies with our aduerſaries.</hi> What are thoſe <hi>very many errors</hi> which they ſay they beare with in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but the doctrines and aſſertions of our Religion, which amidſt their out-cries and clamours that our Religion was not heard of before <hi>Luthers</hi> time, they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues confeſſe to be conteined and taught in the writings of the Fathers, but forſooth the Fathers erred in ſaying as we ſay? Which yet becauſe they hold it would be ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment to their cauſe alwaies to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, therefore, according to the rules of their <hi>Index,</hi> they put them off with cunning and colourable anſwers and exceptions (albeit ſometimes alſo with very lewde and apparant mockeries) when we bring their teſtimonies moſt expreſſe and preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and cleare againſt them. We alleadge <hi>Tertullian</hi> affirming the Emperour to be <note n="n" place="margin">See the place after, Sect. 11.</note> 
               <hi>inferiour to none but God.</hi> They tell vs that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:645:16"/> 
               <hi>Tertullian</hi> was <note n="o" place="margin">Renat. Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent. annot. in Tertul. Apolog cap. 30. <hi>Noluit offendere Genti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es. Caeſaream maieſtatem ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundam hac de cauſa nominat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>loth to offend the Pagans, and therefore did ſo ſpeake,</hi> as if in good earneſt he had not ſo ſpoken. We bring <hi>Agatho</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome profeſsing himſelfe in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe wordes, <note n="p" place="margin">Agath. Epiſt. Synod. 6 Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop. act. 4 <hi>Pro obedientia quam debuimꝰ; vt perſonas, &amp;c. Pro obedientiae ſatisfactione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rere; Noſtra puſillitas quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſſum eſt obſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter impleuit</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to owe obedience to the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, to be carefull to giue ſatisfaction of his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, to performe obediently the Emperours commaundement.</hi> Doct. BISHOP forſooth anſwereth, that <note n="q" place="margin">Reproofe, p. 170. 181.</note> 
               <hi>theſe are but common and vſuall words of courteſie, vttered of cuſtome and courteſie in all Countries.</hi> VVe alleadge <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome,</hi> ſaying that <note n="n" place="margin">Chryſoſt. Op imperſ. in Mat. hom. 11. <hi>Haec vaſa ſanctificata in quibus non eſt verum corpus Chriſti, ſed myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m corporis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in the ſacred veſſels there is not the very true body of Chriſt, but the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his body. Bellarmine</hi> anſwereth, that <note n="o" place="margin">Bellarm. de Sacram. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. <hi>Ab aliquo Beregarij diſcipulo inſerta illi homiliae eſſe videntur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>theſe words ſeeme to be foiſted in by ſome Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Berengarius;</hi> whereas they themſelues haue alwayes ſo printed the words vnto vs out of their own Libraries: &amp; although they ſay in generall, that <note n="p" place="margin">Edit. venet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>584. in marg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oci. <hi>Haec in quibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>da exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaribus deſunt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the wordes are wanting in ſome copies,</hi> yet leſt they ſhould be taken in a lie, doe not name in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar any one copie where they are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, neyther hath any ſuch thing beene obſerued by them, who did formerly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh the ſame worke. As for that which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:645:16"/> he addeth, that <note n="q" place="margin">Bellarm. vt ſupra. <hi>Ad rem non faciunt, nam loquebatur author homiliae devaſis ſacris templi Salomonis</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the words are nothing to the purpoſe, becauſe they are ſpoken of the veſſels of the Temple of Salomon, which Balthaſar a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed, and was therefore puniſhed:</hi> it is a very ſenſeleſſe and wilfull ſhift, becauſe he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe confeſſeth, that <note n="r" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>In illis vaſis non ſolum non crat verum corpus Domini ſed nec myſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um eius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in thoſe veſsels there was no myſtery of Chriſts body at all;</hi> becauſe <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſaith, not thoſe veſſels but theſe, nor wherein <hi>was,</hi> but wherein <hi>is conteyned,</hi> ſpeaking in the preſent tenſe, as of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels which they had then in vſe; becauſe it had beene ridiculous to warne his hearers of a danger in abuſing the veſſels of the Temple of Ieruſalem, which they had not to abuſe; and doth no otherwiſe ſpeake of <hi>Balthaſar,</hi> but as bringing a particular ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample for proofe of a generall Doctrine: that by the puniſhment of <hi>Balthaſar</hi> for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſing the veſſels of the Temple of Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, we are taught how dangerous it is prophanely to defile veſſels of ſacred vſe, as namely the veſſels of our Chriſtian Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>wherein yet is not the very body of Chriſt, but only the myſtery of his body.</hi> But to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then this aſſertion of <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> wee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:645:17"/> 
               <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of Rome affirming that <note n="ſ" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 line">
                     <desc>〈1 line〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Sacraments which we receiue of the body and blood of Chriſt, are a diuine thing, and we are thereby made partakers of the diuine na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and yet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>there ceaſeth not to be the ſubſtance or nature of Bread and Wine.</hi> Which wordes as they aſtoniſhed <note n="t" place="margin">Chemnic. in Exam. Concil. Trident. de Tranſubſtant.</note> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall <hi>Contarenus</hi> in the conference at Ratiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bone, ſo <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo is amazed at them; and though he tooke vpon him <note n="u" place="margin">Bellarm. de Sacram. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>char. cap. 27.</note> to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere them as well as he could, yet durſt not ſet them downe. The matter is plaine by the teſtimony of a Biſhop of Rome, that <hi>there ceaſeth not in the Sacrament to be the ſubſtance or nature of Bread and Wine.</hi> And what will they ſay to it? <note n="x" place="margin">Bellarm. ibid Melch. Canus loc. com. lib. 6. cap. 8.</note> Sometimes for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth the Authour of the booke was not <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of Rome, but another <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſius</hi> Biſhop of Ceſarea in Paleſtina, who was more auncient then he of Rome. And yet <note n="y" place="margin">Bibhoth. ſanct. patrum Tom 4. Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>89.</note> they themſelues as they haue found it, ſo haue alwaies printed it, and doe vnder the name of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of Rome: and the Tract being written in Latine is not likely to be written by <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:645:17"/> Ceſarea, who being of the Greeke Church did vndoubtedly write what hee wrote in the Greeke tongue. But it hath receiued credite as the worke of a renowmed Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of that name, and in all likelihood of <hi>Gelaſius</hi> Biſhop of Rome, by <note n="y" place="margin">Ioan. 1. Epiſt. aduer. Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chian. Biblioth ſanct. Pat. tom. 4. 1589.</note> being cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Biſhop of Rome, <hi>Iohn</hi> the firſt; who was the fourth that ſucceeded after the ſame <hi>Gelaſius.</hi> Therefore <hi>Gregory de Valentia</hi> ſeeing little boote in that anſwer, ſticketh not to ſay both concerning <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doret</hi> and <hi>Gelaſius,</hi> that <note n="z" place="margin">Greg. de Val. de Tranſubſt. cap. 8. <hi>Antequa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quaeſtio illa de tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione in Eccleſia palam agitare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, minime mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nus aut al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er, aut e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam aliqui ex vetcribus minus conſideratè &amp; recte hac dere ſenſerint &amp; ſcripſerint.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>before the queſtion of tranſubſtantiation was debated in the Church, it is no maruelif one or ſome of the ancient Writers did both thinke and write vnaduiſedly and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe concerning this matter;</hi> And againe, <hi>If</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Idem, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. de Idolol. l 3. c. 5. <hi>Si maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Gelaſius tanquam Dector aliquis nihil vt Pontifex deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minans, &amp; vnus item aut alter ex Patr bus hac <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>re lapſus erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re fuiſſet, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rte nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bem aliorum teſtium.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gelaſius as a priuate Doctor, not as Pope to determine; and ſome one or other of the Fathers haue erred herein, yet we haue for vs a cloude of witneſſes.</hi> So then <hi>Gelaſius</hi> in priuate ſaid the ſame that wee doe, and was minded as we are, that there ceaſeth not in the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee the ſubſtance of Bread and Wine; but he erred therein: and if he had ſet him downe in his Conſiſtory Chaire
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:645:18"/> (O abſurd mockery) he would have been of another ſpirit, and haue ſpoken as the Papiſts ſpeake, whereas notwithſtanding he wrote theſe words in a dogmaticall tract againſt the two Hereſies of <hi>Neſtorius</hi> and <hi>Eutyches,</hi> and therefore muſt be taken defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitiuely to reſolue againſt that which is now taught in the Church of Rome. Not ſo, ſaith Doct. <hi>Biſhop,</hi> for though the worſt come to the worſt, yet <note n="b" place="margin">Doct. Biſhop Reproofe, p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>62.</note> 
               <hi>the ſentence may haue a good meaning, and may ſtand well with our doctrine: for the nature of bread doth not wholly ceaſe to be in the Sacrament, becauſe the forme, ſauor, and taſt of bread doe still remaine, though the whole inward ſubſtance be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the body of Chriſt.</hi> Marke this well, I pray you; <hi>there ceaſeth not to be the ſubſtance of bread;</hi> that is, there ceaſeth not to be the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents of bread, the forme, ſauor and taſte of bread: <hi>there ceaſeth not to be the ſubſtance of bread;</hi> that is, the whole ſubſtance of bread is turned into the body of Chriſt. May wee not thinke that they imagine themſelues to haue to do with beaſts, and not with men, that wil ſeeke to put them
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:645:18"/> off with ſuch anſwers and expoſitions, as theſe are? Againe we alleadge <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> affirming it <note n="c" place="margin">Epiphan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Ioan. Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſolom <hi>Cum hoc vidiſſem (velum pendens habens imagi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nem quaſi Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti vel ſancti cuiuſdam) in Eccleſia Chriſti contra authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem ſcriptura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum hominis pendere imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, ſcidi illud, &amp;c. Eiuſmodi vela quae contra religionem no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtram veniunt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to be againſt Chriſtian Religion to haue in Churches the Images of Chriſt and his Saints,</hi> and ſhewing that he himſelfe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into a Church, and finding a veyle wherein ſuch an Image was painted, did cut the veyle in peeces. <hi>Alphonſus de Caſtro</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs, that <note n="d" place="margin">Alphonſ. de Caſt. lib. 8. tit. Imago. <hi>Res non crat adeo aperta nec deilla re quod ſciam vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Eccleſia illo tempore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finierat.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>this matter of Images was not then ſo cleare, neyther had the Church defined any thing thereof:</hi> but now <note n="e" place="margin">Gregor. de Valent. Apol. de idololat. l 2. c. 7. <hi>Si maximè fact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m ill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d Epiphanij ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plocatum eſſet, nonnè plus pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deris apud nos Eccleſiae totius authoritas at<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vſus habere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the authority of the Church,</hi> ſaith the Valentian Ieſuite, <hi>is to be of more weight with vs then the authority of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius.</hi> Yet we bring the Councell of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberis,</hi> ſaying, <note n="f" place="margin">Concil. Eliber. ca. 36. <hi>Placuit in Eccleſia picturas eſſe non debere, ne quod colitur aut adoratur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>parietibus d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pingatur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We will that there be no pictures in Churches, that that which is worſhipped and adored, be not painted vpon the wall.</hi> VVhere <hi>Bellarm</hi> reciting diuers of his fellows an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers, &amp; truſting to none of them, cutteth off the matter briefly thus: <note n="g" place="margin">Bellar. de imag. ſanct. cap. 9. <hi>Quicquid concilium ſtatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit, &amp;c. contra nos tantum eſſe poteſt concilium 19. Epiſcoporum quod prouinciale fuit, minimè confirmatum, &amp; in alijs decretis videtur crraſſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer that Councell decreed, there can be againſt vs onely a Councell of nineteene Biſhops, which was but Prouincial, and not confirmed, and ſeemeth in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:645:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> Decrees to haue erred.</hi> VVe bring <hi>Hierom</hi> determining of the bookes of Canonicall Scripture as we doe, and <note n="h" place="margin">Hieron. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. galeat. <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pientia quae vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go Solomonis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribitur, eſt Ieſu filij Syrach liber, &amp; Tobias, &amp; Iudith, &amp; Paſtor non ſunt in Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>none.</hi>
               </note> excluding from the Canon the ſame that wee exclude, the bookes of VViſedome, Eccleſiaſticus, To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie, Iudith, &amp;c. <hi>Melchior Canus</hi> turneth him off in a word thus; <note n="i" place="margin">Melch. Can. loc. comm. l. 2. c. 11. <hi>Nec ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum eſt in decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendis libris Canonicis Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae regulam eſſe Hieronymum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierome is no rule to the Church for the determining of the Canonicall bookes;</hi> whereas <hi>Hierome</hi> ſetteth not downe his owne opinion only, but the iudgment and practiſe of the Church; <note n="k" place="margin">Hieron. praef in lib. <hi>Solom. Iudith &amp; Tobiae &amp; Maccabaeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum libros legit quidem Eccleſia ſed eas inter Canonicas ſcripturas uon recipit:</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The Church readeth them, but yet doth not receiue them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Canonicall Scriptures. Chryſoſtome</hi> layeth vpon the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſome aſperſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <note n="l" place="margin">Chryſoſt. in Mat. hom. 45. <hi>Conſidera tam matris quàm frotrum impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunitatem, &amp;c. Ambitione qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam &amp; oſtenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moti &amp;c. Patet inani quadam gloria illos com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motos fuiſſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ambition, oſtentation, and vaine glory:</hi> whereby we ſhew his iudgement, that the bleſſed Virgin was not without ſinne, but ſtood in neede of her ſonne to be her Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour. The Inquiſition of Venice hath giuen him a checke in the margent, <note n="m" place="margin">Edit. Venet. 1583. in marg. loci. <hi>Hic author excedit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Here the authour goeth too farre:</hi> and <hi>Pererius</hi> the Ieſuite ſomewhat more ſharpely; <note n="n" place="margin">Perer. <hi>Chryſoſtomus &amp; veritatis &amp; pietatis terminos exceſſit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome paſsed the bounds of truth and pietie.</hi> Of <hi>Auſtins</hi> doctrine and iudgement con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:645:19"/> originall ſinne, <hi>Pighius</hi> doubted not to ſay, that it is <note n="o" place="margin">Pigh. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trou. de pecc. Orig pag. 7. b. <hi>Non ſolum quod certa non ſit, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mò qd</hi> 
                  <hi>certò falſa ſit. &amp;</hi> pag. 35. b. <hi>vides in quàm abſurda dicta Pelagij ratiuncu la Auguſtinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dere coegerit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>not onely not certaine, but certainly falſe,</hi> and that <hi>by a petite reaſon of</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagius <hi>he was driuen to ſpeake abſurdly thereof.</hi> The ſame <hi>Auſtin</hi> in diuers bookes againſt the Pelagians ſoundly deliuereth the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of the predeſtination and grace of God; but <note n="p" place="margin">Oſor. de iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. l. 9. <hi>Nulla eſt in ſcholis ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> maiore contentatione ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> minore rationu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> praeſidio defenſa, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Oſorius</hi> a Popiſh Biſhop in a worke written at large, purpoſely and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſedly diſputeth againſt him. And thus haue they at their pleaſure vilified and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graced all the auncient hiſtories of the Church. <hi>Eeuſebius</hi> is reiected by <hi>Melchior Canus,</hi> as <note n="q" place="margin">Melch. Can. loc. com. l. 11. c. 6. <hi>Ariana haere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeos defenſor eſſe cognoſcitur ex Synod. Nicen. 2.</hi>
               </note> a <hi>defendor of the Arrian hereſie,</hi> and his hiſtory is branded and condemned for <note n="r" place="margin">Diſt. 15. <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta Romana. Historia Euſebij Pamphili Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crypha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> Apocryphal by their Canon law. <hi>Ruffinus</hi> is taxed by <note n="ſ" place="margin">Bellarm. de Rom. Pont. l. 2. cap. 13. <hi>Falſa expoſitio eſt, &amp;c. Non rectè Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilij ſententiam Ruffin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> expoſuit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Bellarm.</hi> for expounding falſely the Councell of Nice; &amp; for reckoning the Canonical Scriptures, as we do, according as he ſaith, to the tradition of the Fathers, is noted by <hi>Canus</hi> as <note n="t" place="margin">Melch. Can. loc. com. l. 2. c. 11. <hi>Ruffinus, pace lectoris dictum ſit, Patrum traditiones ignorauit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>being ignorant of the tradition of the Fathers. Socrates</hi> is traduced by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> alſo, as <note n="u" place="margin">Bellar. de bon. oper. in part. l. 2. c. 15. <hi>Dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Socratem non multum fidei mereri cùm &amp; Nouatianus &amp; Aërianus fue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. &amp;</hi> de cult, Sanct. c. 10. <hi>Dico fuiſſe Nouatianum ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> teſtimoniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eius in dogmatibꝰ vllius eſſe momenti.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a Nouatian and Aerian
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:645:20"/> hereticke, worthy of little credite,</hi> and is noted by him, as telling <note n="x" place="margin">Idem de Clericis, cap. 20. Socrates l. 5. c 21. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 words">
                        <desc>〈◊◊◊◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>three manifeſt lies at once. Sozomen</hi> is likewiſe contemptuouſly reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by him as <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>d. Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes &amp; Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menus haereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ci. <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>zomem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> S. Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> multa, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> quit, ment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>an Hereticke and a liar</hi> his Hiſtory being cenſured by him out of <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory as full of lies. Theodoret</hi> is taxed for a party. <hi>Neſtorian</hi> and <note n="z" place="margin">Melch. Can. loc. com. l. 11. c. 6. <hi>Illiuſmodi er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantium patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a hiſtoriae <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leuant &amp; autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatem &amp; fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>his defence of them,</hi> ſaith <hi>Canus, impeacheth the authority and credit of his Story. Nicephorus</hi> with <hi>Maldonatus</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Maldonat. praefat. in Luc. <hi>Nicephorus quantam fidem mercat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r abalijs malim aeſtimari quam a me dici: mihi temper au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ior eſt viſus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>deſerueth like credite, and ſeemeth to him too preſumptuous and bold.</hi> Thus whereas they exclaime againſt our modeſt and iuſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt the Fathers, ſuch as are taught and approued by the Fathers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, and by which we ſubiect them on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the word of God; they themſelues are altogether impudent in this behalfe, vſing the Fathers as counters, to be ſomewhat when they liſt, &amp; when they liſt nothing; yet as cyphers to be of no vſe, but onely as they ſerue to adde to them. Like guardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and tutors, ſo they diſpoſe of them as their wardes and ſchollers, to ſpeake when they bid them, or otherwiſe to hold their peace; not hereby to yeeld authority to the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:645:20"/> word of God, or to giue place to, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> but to giue way to whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer deuiſes and traditions they themſelues liſt to bring into the Church: yea, to that deſperate paſſe they are brought by the writings of the Fathers, as that they ſee they cannot ſtand but by offering violence vnto them. Therefore as the olde Heretickes tooke vpon them to be <note n="b" place="margin">Iren. lib. 3. c. 1. <hi>Sicut quidam audent dicere gloriantes ſe eſſe emendatores A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolorum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>emendatores Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum, the reformers of the Apoſtles;</hi> ſo do they take vpon them to be <hi>expurgatores &amp; emen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datores Patrum, the purgers and correctors of the Fathers;</hi> altering and chopping and changing their workes, putting in and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out, falſifying and corrupting moſt ſhamefully all, both their written and printed books. In a word, like <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, what they cannot vntie they wil cut, not with a knife, but with a ſword or an Axe, and hauing abandoned the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and vſe of, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> they are at a paſſe with all other authorities, and muniments of faith, ſaying with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, <note n="c" place="margin">Pſal. 2. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Let vs breake their bondes aſunder, and caſt away their cordes from vs:</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 12. 4.</note> 
               <hi>With our
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:645:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> tongues we will preuaile, we are they that ought to ſpeake, who is Lord ouer vs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6 But for our direction in the right way, let vs now hear what the Lord ſaith; where firſt we are to note, what he biddeth vs to do for the finding of the way; <hi>ſtand, behold, and aske for the way.</hi> Secondly, what mark he giueth wherby we are to take knowledge of the way; which conſiſteth in this, that he calleth it <hi>the old way,</hi> affirming the ſame to be <hi>the good way.</hi> As touching the firſt, we know that the way faring man, comming to a place where there are many waies and turnings, becommeth at a ſtand. He will not go on at all aduenture, but ſtaieth and looketh about him; he coaſteth the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, and caſteth with himſelfe which may be moſt likely to be the way; and for the more aſſurance asketh and enquireth of them of whom hee can preſume that hee ſhall learne the way. By which compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon the holy Ghoſt heere inſtructeth vs what to doe, when wee fall into queſtion and doubt of our ſpirituall way: Firſt, he willeth vs to <hi>ſtand vpon the wayes,</hi> as to deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:645:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> and deuiſe, warning vs in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe to doe nothing headlongly and raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but to conſider earneſtly and carefully, what way we make choice of: For as in all things, ſo ſpecially in Religion precipita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and headlong wilfulneſſe is greatly to be condemned. For religion is a matter of greateſt conſequence; where to vſe the wordes of <hi>Tertullian,</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Tertul de patient. <hi>Cuius iudicium in ſuos non in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pede aut pileo vertitur ſed in aeternitate aut poenae aut ſalutis</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the queſtion is not of bondage or freedome, but of eternity, eyther of puniſhment or ſaluation.</hi> And therefore here to deale at all aduenture, and in the cauſe of God, and hazard of ſoules health, to goe on raſhly and without regard, and to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a Religion without reaſon, argueth a retchleſſe and lewd mind; which we may not wonder, if God ſeuerely reuenge, as a matter of high indignity to himſelfe. For which cauſe we cannot doubt but that the indignation and curſe of God lieth vpon a number of our Recuſants, who hand ouer head, and without any due regard haue embraced that damnable way, and haue impiouſly confederated themſelues with the enemies of God, of their Prince and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:645:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> countrey, inthralling themſelues to Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, the man of ſinne, the ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and yeelding themſelues to be ledde by him to their owne deſtruction; euen by him who in infinite pride hath taken vpon him, that <note n="f" place="margin">Diſt. 40. <hi>Si Papa ſuae &amp; fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern ſalutis neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligens, &amp;c. Innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merabiles populos cateruatim ſecum ducit primo man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipio gehennae cum ipſo plagis multis in eternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vapulaturus, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius culpas iſhic redarguere prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumit mortalium nullus, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>though he led de with him innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſoules to hell to periſh with him for euer, yet may no mortall man take vpon him to reproue him.</hi> And this many doe, ſpecially women of curioſity and ſingularity, deſirous to ſeeme ſomwhat by being that, that others are not, and thinking the name of a Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to be a trimme name, becauſe thereby there is a difference made betwixt them, and, as they conceiue, the vulgar ſort of men, when in the meane time as touching iudgement and conſcience, they haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to ſatisfie either others or themſelues why they doe that which they doe: which wantonneſſe and pride of oppoſition, iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſerueth to be chaſtened by lawes, and the rod of correction is neceſſarily to bee vſed, to ſtay the courſe of this wilfull folly; to cauſe ſuch headlong perſons to ſtand, and to bethinke and aduiſe themſelues of that they doe.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:645:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>7 For ſo doth the Prophet teach vs, not onely to <hi>ſtand,</hi> but alſo to <hi>beholde:</hi> wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling vs thereby to vſe our eyes, that is, our iudgement and vnderſtanding, to eſteeme and conſider of the wayes that are before vs. For albeit our owne vnderſtanding of it ſelfe, ſuffice not to informe vs as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the truth of faith and religion towards God, yet our ſight and iudgement out of the notice of ſome common and generall principles auayleth ſo farre, as that we are able thereby to ſay, that this or that is not true Religion, becauſe faſehood in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on commonly hath ſomewhat, wherein, if we vſe our eyes, we may ſee the Image of him that is the Authour thereof. And ſo the caſe ſtandeth in Popery, where amidſt all their varniſhes and colours, there are ſome things ſo groſſe, ſo palpably abſurd, as that a blinde man with his fingers and by very touch may diſcerne, and feele the abhominations of them. For their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts and practiſe of equiuocation and mentall euaſion; their doctrine of the Popes power to depoſe Kings and Princes,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:645:23"/> and to giue licence to their ſubiects contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to their ſworne alleageance, to riſe in a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mes againſt them, &amp; eyther by violence or treachery to kill them, and that with the merite of remiſsion of ſinnes and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall life; their aſſertion, <note n="g" place="margin">Tho. Aquin. p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> q 80. art. 3. in corp. <hi>Eliam ſi mus vel canis <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſtiam conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratam mandu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret, ſubſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a corporis Chriſts non deſin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t eſſe ſub ſpeciebus, &amp;c. Quidam dixerunt quod ſtatim cum Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitur a mure vel cane, deſinit ibi eſſe corpus Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſti; quod de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogat veritati Sacramenti.</hi>
               </note> that Dogges and Mice, and Swine eating their conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Hoaſt, doe eate into their bowels the very body and bloud of Chriſt; their ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable paradoxe, <note n="h" place="margin">Coſter. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid cap. 15. <hi>Sacerdos ſi for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicetur aut domi concubinam fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueat, tamet ſi graui ſacrilegio ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe obſtringat, gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ius tamen peccat ſi contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t matrimoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi>
               </note> that it is more law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for a Prieſt to commit fornication then to marry a wife; <note n="l" place="margin">Bellar. de A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>grat. &amp; Stat. pecc. l. 2. c. 18. <hi>Non peccat. Magiſtratus ſi m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cibꝰ cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um locum vrbis incolendum attribuat.</hi>
               </note> their defence of publicke and common Stewes; their falling downe to worſhip ſtocks and ſtones, and to pray and offer to them; their Seruice and prayers in a ſtrange and vnknowen tongue; their maiming of the Sacrament by admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring it in one kinde, contrary to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe inſtitution and example of Chriſt in the Goſpell, and that with a <hi>Non obſtante</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">
                  <hi>Concil. Conſtant. Seſſ. 13.</hi> Lic et Chriſtus poſt coenam inſtituerit &amp; ſuis d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcipulis adminiſtrauerit ſub vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſpecie panis &amp; vini hoc venerabile Sacramentum, tamen hoc non obſtante conſuetudo quòd a laicis tantummodò ſub ſpecie Panis ſuſcipiatur, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benda eſt pro lege, quam non licet reprobare, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>This notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, yet the cuſtome of adminiſtring to the lay people, onely in the forme of bread, ſhall be
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:645:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> taken for a law;</hi> Theſe, I ſay, and ſundry o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their doctrines and doings are ſuch and ſo contrary to the common ſenſe of Chriſtian piety, as that of them who haue had occaſion and meanes to take notice of them, and yet perſiſt and goe forward in their euill way, wee haue iuſt occaſion to conceiue that which the Apoſtle ſaith, that <note n="l" place="margin">2. Cor. 4. 4.</note> 
               <hi>the God of this world hath blinded their eyes, that the light of the glorious Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt ſhould not ſhine vnto them:</hi> And againe, that <note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 1. 28.</note> 
               <hi>God hath giuen them ouer to a reprobate ſenſe, to doe the things that are not conuenient,</hi> and hath ſet vpon them a marke of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate illuſion, whereof the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaketh, <note n="n" place="margin">2. Theſ. 2. 10. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Becauſe they regarded not the loue of the truth that they might be ſaued, therefore God ſhall ſend them strong deluſion, that they may beleeue lies, that they may be damned, which beleeued not the truth, but tooke pleaſure in vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8 The next thing that is to be done, is <hi>to aske for the way.</hi> Now no man doubteth, but that it is expedient and neceſſary ſo to doe, but the queſtion is, of whom we are
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:645:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> to aske? Whom ſhall I aske that I may be ſure to receiue of him certaine and true an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, which is the way of eternall life? Let me goe through all the Religions and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsions in the world, Proteſtants, Papiſts, Browniſts, Arians, Pelagians, euery one will ſay of that that he himſelfe followeth that it is the right way. Who is now the Iudge amongſt all theſe to giue vs certaine aſſurance and warrant, which is the way indeede? And whom ſhall wee thinke to be this Iudge but God himſelfe, who as he is the end whereto we goe, ſo is the onely directour of the way whereby wee are to come vnto him? But here the troubled minde asketh againe, How ſhall I come to aske of God? how ſhall I heare his voyce to receiue anſwer from him? Let vs take the anſwer of this queſtion from S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Hierome,</hi> who demaunding, <note n="o" place="margin">Hieron. in Pſ. 86. <hi>Dominus narrauit &amp; quomodo narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit? Non verbo ſed Scriptura. In cuius Scriptura? In populorum, &amp;c. quae Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tura populis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus legitur, hoc eſt, vt omnes intelligant, &amp;c. Principes Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae &amp; princepes Chriſti non ſcripſerunt pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis ſed vniuerſo populo, &amp;c. non vt pauci intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent ſed vt omnes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>How will the Lord ſhew or declare?</hi> anſwereth, <hi>Not by word or voyce but in the Scripture. In whoſe Scripture?</hi> Marry ſaith he, <hi>In the Scripture of the people,</hi> which he noteth to be ſo called, becauſe <hi>it is read vnto all people, that is,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſo as that al may
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:645:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> vnderſtand;</hi> becauſe <hi>the Princes of Chriſt,</hi> that is, the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts, <hi>did write not for a few, but for the whole people, not that a few, but that all may vnderſtand.</hi> God then hath giuen thee his holy Scripture, &amp; hath attemperated the ſame to thy capacity and vnderſtanding, that there thou mayeſt aske and receiue anſwere of him, which the way is wherein thou art to walke, that thou mayeſt obteine eternall life. And hereof ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop of Rome (a farre o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man then are thoſe Vipers and Aſpes that now are bred out of the Church of Rome.) <note n="p" place="margin">Gregor. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral. l. 16. c. 16. <hi>Per Scripturam Deus loquitur omne quod vult.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>By the Scripture God telleth vs all his will.</hi> 
               <note n="q" place="margin">Idem. Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit. in 1. Reg. c. 3. <hi>Quid cor &amp; animam dei niſi ſacram. eius Scripturam accipimus?</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>What doe we vnderſtand,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>by the heart and ſoule of God, but his holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture?</hi> as to giue vs to vnderſtand, that if we deſire to come ſo neere vnto God, as to haue him poure forth his <hi>heart and ſoule</hi> vnto vs, we muſt expect and looke for the ſame in his holy Scriptures. And therefore is it that our Sauiour Chriſt vſeth that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <note n="a" place="margin">Iohn 5. 39.</note> 
               <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye thinke to haue eternall life, and they are they that teſtifie of me.</hi> Heereby doth God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:645:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> the promiſe that of olde hee made vnto his people, <note n="r" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 30 21.</note> 
               <hi>Thou ſhalt heare a voyce be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hinde thee, ſaying This is the way, walke in the ſame.</hi> Of which way the Prophet ſaith fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſay. 35. 8.</note> 
               <hi>There ſhall be a path and a way, and the way ſhall be called holy; the polluted ſhall not paſſe by it, for God ſhall be with them</hi> (that is, with his people that ſeeke him) <hi>and walke in the way; and the fooles (the ſimple) ſhall not erre,</hi> namely becauſe <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 19. 7.</note> 
               <hi>the law of the Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth wiſedome and vnderſtanding vnto the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pro. 1. 4.</note> 
               <hi>and to a childe knowledge and diſcretion.</hi> Very notable is that of <hi>Optatus,</hi> and much to be marked in this behalfe, when being at queſtion with the Donatiſts, whether it were lawfull to rebaptize or not, hee ſaith thus, <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <hi>Optat. cont. Parme. l. 5.</hi> Vos dicitis, Licet, nos dicimus, Non li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cet. Inter ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrum licet &amp; non licet noſtrum nutant &amp; re: migant animae populorum. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo vobis credat nemo nobis om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes contentioſi homines ſumus. Quaerendi ſunt Iudices. Si Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiani; de vtra<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> parte dari non poſſunt, quia ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs veritas im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditur. Deforis quaerendus eſt Iudex. Si Paga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, non poteſt noſſe Chriſtiana ſecreta. Si Iudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, nimicus eſt Chriſtiani bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmatis. Ergo in terris hac de re nullum poterit reperiri iudicium. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lo quaerendus eſt index, ſed vtquid pulſa mus ad calum cum habemus hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in Euangelio; teſtamentum inquam, &amp;c. Ergo voluntas eius ſicut in teſtamento ſic in Euan gelio inquiratur.</note> 
               <hi>You ſay, it is lawfull and we ſay, it is not lawfull. Betwixt your yea and our nay the ſoules of the people wauer and ſtand in doubt: let no man beleeue vs, let no man beleeue you; we are all contentious men. Wee muſt enquire for Iudges betwixt vs. If of Chriſtians, they can be giuen of neither part of vs, becauſe by part-ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:645:25"/> the truth is hindered. We muſt looke for one abroad. If a Pagan, he cannot know the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret of Chriſtian faith. If a Iew, he is an enemy of Chriſtian baptiſme. Therefore vpon earth no iudgement can be found hereof</hi> (little did hee thinke that the Pope in this caſe is to be the Iudge) <hi>we muſt require a Iudge from heauen. But why,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>do we knocke at heauen, when we haue one here in the Goſpell, euen the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt? As in his Will or Teſtament, ſo in the Gospell let vs require what his will is.</hi> Thus ſpake <hi>Optatus</hi> in a caſe all one with ours, and plainly teacheth vs, who it is that muſt be the Iudge, to end amongſt vs all Controuerſies concerning the right way, euen the Teſtament of Chriſt, the word of the Goſpell, by which Chriſt being in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſtill ſpeaketh vnto vs to giue aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere of that which we aske of him. Now we know this offendeth and galleth the Church of Rome, and they gnaw their tongues for anger at the hearing of it. As <hi>Origen</hi> ſaith, <note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>Origen. in Num. ho. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Super omnia eis est tormentorum genera &amp; ſuper omnes paenas ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quem videant verbo Dei ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram dare, ſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uinae lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis &amp; myſteria ſcripturarum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentis ſtudijs perquirentem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>it is a torment to the Diuels, to ſee a man giuen to the reading of the Scriptures,</hi> ſo is it a torment to them to heare the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:645:26"/> people inuited to the Scriptures, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed there to aske of God concerning the way of life. They repine, they wraſtle, they caſt in ſcruples and doubts, they doe all that may be done to diſcourage men from making vſe of that which God hath giuen to be the ſpeciall meanes and helpe of our ſaluation. But the more they rage in this behalfe, ſo much the more let vs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge and accept the gift of God, and endeauour that <note n="z" place="margin">Ambroſ. in Heb. 5. <hi>Quomo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>runt ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus noſtri exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſſe? Vti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ex vſit &amp; fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> lectione ſanctarum ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turarum, &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>by vſe and often reading and meditation of Scriptures,</hi> as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, <hi>we may</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 5. 14.</note> 
               <hi>haue our wits exerciſed to diſcerne betwixt good and euill;</hi> eſteeming by right reaſon, becauſe the late <hi>Ballancer of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> will haue the matter to be weighed <note n="b" place="margin">Prudent. Ballance of Religion in the Epiſtle.</note> 
               <hi>by naturall and right reaſon;</hi> that it is more ſafe for vs to commit our ſelues to that where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is no queſtion, then to that wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of there is queſtion, and becauſe al men are queſtionable, and doe queſtion one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; therefore to repaire to the Scriptures, and there to aske and ſeeke the way, where no man dare denie but that it is the voyce of God, the voyce of Ieſus Chriſt, which by
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:645:26"/> his Prophets and Apoſtles, vpon whom <note n="c" place="margin">Ephe. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>the houſhold of God are built,</hi> giueth anſwere to vs. To which purpoſe we may obſerue that which <hi>S. Auſtin</hi> ſaith, <note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. in 1. Ioan. Tr. 2. <hi>Contra inſid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſos <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrores Deus voluit pon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re firmamentum in Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ipturis; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra quas nullus audet loqui qui q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>quo modo ſe vult videri Chriſtianum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Againſt deceitfull errours God would ſet vs a Fortreſſe or Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warke in the holy Scriptures, againſt which no man dare ſpeake which will in any ſort be taken for a Chriſtian man.</hi> And of the vſe of theſe Scriptures, <hi>Gregorie</hi> Biſhop of Rome telleth vs thus: <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregor. in Cantic. cap. 5</hi> Sancti viri ſe conſilijs Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae ex toto ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicunt, vt vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licet nihil agant niſi quod ex re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>criptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum audiunt; &amp;c quae fluenta pleniſſima di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuntur, quia de quibuſcun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſcruplis in Scripturis Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium quaeritur, ſine minoratione de omnibus ad plenum inueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Holy men doe wholly addict them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to the counſels of the Scripture, ſo as that they doe nothing but what they heare by anſwer of the Scriptures; which,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>are called full streames or riuers, becauſe of whatſoeuer ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or doubts we aske counſell in the Scriptures; we finde it to the full of all things without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Vnderſtand it according to the words of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> 
               <note n="f" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt. in 2. Theſſ. hom.</hi> 3. Omnia clarae ſunt &amp; manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta ex Scripturis diuinis: quecun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> neceſſaria ſunt, manifeſta ſunt.</note> 
               <hi>All things are manifeſt and cleare by the holy Scriptures; whatſoeuer things are neceſſary, they are manifeſt.</hi> In a word, of the Scriptures S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> moſt comfortably telleth, that <note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Auguſt. de vtil. credendi. cap. 6.</hi> Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè ita modificata vt nemo inde haurire non poſſit quod ſibi ſatis eſt, ſi modò ad hauriendum de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotè ac piè, vt vera religio poſcit, accedat.</note> 
               <hi>the doctrine thereof is ſo tempered, as that there is no man but may drawe from
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:645:27"/> thence that that is ſufficient for himſelfe</hi> (thogh not ſufficient for the anſwering and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of al maner queſtions and doubts, yet ſufficient for himſelfe, for his owne ſoules health) <hi>ſo that he come to draw with de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion and piety, as true Religion requireth he ſhould doe:</hi> for to ſuch GOD himſelfe is a teacher, not only outwardly by his word, but alſo inwardly by his ſpirit, enlightning their vnderſtanding, &amp; guiding their harts to conceiue aright of his way, giuing them that anſwere, whereof <hi>Gregory</hi> ſpeaketh, when interpreting <note n="h" place="margin">Greg. Moral. l 35. c. 3. <hi>Homini d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rugare eſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>pect<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>entem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>gnoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ere. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>mdore au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>Det <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt, eſt eum qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> benè h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter neſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entem cognouerit interms inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bus erudire.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>our asking of God to be the acknowledgement of our owne ignorance in the ſight of God,</hi> he expoundeth <hi>Gods anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be his inſtructing of them by inward in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirations,</hi> 
               <note n="i" place="margin">Leo in Natiu. Serm. 5. <hi>Quis ad haec id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neus, niſi qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p. Dei &amp; docetur &amp; regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, dicente Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Nos autem non ſpiritum huiꝰ mund. accep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mꝰ &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nte eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Dauid; Bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus quem tu e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieris, domine, &amp; de lege tua docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris eum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>who doe humbly acknowledge their owne ignorance before him.</hi> And of this teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and anſwering <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of Rome ſpeaketh, when hauing ſignified the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty of holding the right way amongſt ſo many opinions, and ſo many falſhoods, carrying ſhew and likelihood of truth, as hath beene before ſaid, he addeth, <hi>Who is fit for this, but hee that is both taught and gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:645:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the ſpirit of God, according to that which the Apoſtle ſaith,</hi> 
               <note n="k" place="margin">1. Cor. 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Wee haue not receiued the ſpirit of this world, but the ſpirit which is of God, that we may know the things that are gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto vs of God; and as Dauid ſaith,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 94. 12.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed is he whom thou inſtructeſt, O Lord, and teacheſt him by thy law.</hi> Then indeede are wee truely taught, and then doe we effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually and truely learne, not when wee onely reade the law, but when God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe teacheth vs by his law; and thus hee teacheth all them who in the ſtudy of his law do faithfully &amp; deuoutly aske of him. And by this inſpired teaching God proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, as in the time of Chriſt, ſo now alſo amidſt al the illuſions of Antichriſt, amidſt all the ſeducements, and Heretickes, and falſe teachers, amidſt all the ſtumbling blockes that Satan caſteth in the way, that <note n="m" place="margin">Mat. 11. 19.</note> 
               <hi>Wiſedome</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>is iuſtified of her children,</hi> and they without faile <note n="n" place="margin">Acts 13. 48.</note> 
               <hi>beleeue whom God hath ordained vnto eternall life.</hi> As for thoſe <note n="o" place="margin">Ioſ. 7. 21.</note> Achans, that in the midſt of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell are in loue with <hi>Babyloniſh garments</hi> and thinke themſelues to be adorned and bew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified thereby, they ſhall we are the ſhame
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:645:28" rendition="simple:additions"/> and confuſion thereof, they ſhall <note n="p" place="margin">2. Tim. 3. 13.</note> 
               <hi>grow worſe and worſe, deceiuing and being deceiued,</hi> till <note n="q" place="margin">Eſay 8. 15.</note> 
               <hi>they ſtumble and fall, and be broken in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> and periſh, neuer to riſe againe.</p>
            <p n="9">9 It followeth now what the marke is whereby God here deſcribeth the right and good way, which to that purpoſe hee termeth <hi>the old way. The old way,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>is the good way.</hi> Where we may iuſtly deride the folly of the Papiſts, who call their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion <hi>the old way, the old Religion;</hi> whereas here we ſee the faithfull inſtructed as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the old way, when as yet there was neither Pope, nor Papiſt, nor Papiſtrie, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were thoſe ſuperſtitions knowen, which they now ſo much commend as the onely way to come to God. Certaine it is indeed, that <hi>the olde way</hi> is the onely right way, and what is moſt auncient is moſt true; but in this they dally and much de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e men, that they take the name of the <hi>old way</hi> of that that hath beene ſome ages and generations before vs; whereas the rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning of that that is to bee termed <hi>olde,</hi> ought to be from the beginning: neyther
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:645:28"/> ſhould that in this caſe bee called <hi>old;</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt which, that exception ſtandeth which our Sauiour vſeth in the Goſpell, <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 19. 8.</note> 
               <hi>from the beginning it was not ſo.</hi> Of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation to make the better vſe, we are to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that as from the beginning to the end there is but <hi>one body</hi> of the Church; ſo there is alſo but <note n="ſ" place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 4. 5.</note> 
               <hi>one faith,</hi> 
               <note n="t" place="margin">2. Cor. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3.</note> 
               <hi>one and the ſame ſpirit of faith,</hi> as the Apoſtle teacheth. <note n="u" place="margin">Leo de paſſ. Dom. Ser. 14. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na fides iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat vniuerſorum temporum ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctos.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>One faith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Leo, iuſtifieth the Saints of all times;</hi> 
               <note n="u" place="margin">Idem in Nat. Dom. Serm. 3. Fides qua viui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus nulla fuit aetate diu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſa.</note> 
               <hi>the faith whereby we liue was not diuers in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny age.</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Auguſt. de Nat. &amp; grat. c. 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Ea fides iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtos ſanauit an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquos quae ſanat &amp; nos.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The ſame faith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin, ſaued the iuſt of olde that now ſaueth vs:</hi> 
               <note n="y" place="margin">Idem in Ioan Tract. 45. <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pora variata ſunt, non fides. Mutetus eſt ſonꝰ venturus eſt, &amp; venit; eadem tamen fides v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> coniungit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the tenſes are diuers,</hi> they ſpake of Chriſt in the future tenſe, <hi>Chriſt to come,</hi> we ſpeake of him in the preter tenſe, <hi>Chriſt already come; but there is no difference of faith.</hi> They differed from vs in outward ſignes and ſacraments; they had circumciſion, and the cloud, and the redde Sea, and Manna, and the rocke; we haue in ſtead thereof Baptiſme and the Lords Supper: but <note n="z" place="margin">Auguſt. ibid. <hi>In diuerſis ſignis cadem fides.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in this diuerſity of ſignes there is the ſame faith.</hi> Therefore of thoſe auncient faithfull the ſame S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſaith, that <note n="a" place="margin">Idem Cont. 2 Epiſt. Pelag. l. 3. c. 4. <hi>Eadem ſides &amp; in illis qui non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum nomine ſed reipſa ſuerunt Chriſtia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, &amp; in illis qui <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> c. nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>though not in name, yet in deede they were Christians,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:645:29"/> euen as the Apoſtle alſo ſaith of them, that <note n="b" place="margin">1. Cor. 10. 2, 3</note> 
               <hi>they were baptized, and did eate the ſame ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall meat, and drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke</hi> that we now doe. This is a firme and a ſure foundation; and hereby wee vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that <hi>the old way</hi> wherein wee are to walke, the olde faith whereby wee attaine eternall life, is the ſame with the faith of the Patriarches, and Prophets, and righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fathers from the beginning of the world. Let vs then looke vpon them, and conſider with our ſelues; Were they Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts? <hi>Abel, Enoch, Abraham, Iſaac, Jacob, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> were they Papiſts? Had they a Pope to goe to for indulgences and Pardons to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer their ſoules from Purgatory? Or was any of them a Pope to giue any ſuch? Did they one call vpon another, and pray one to another when they were dead? Did <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> pray to <hi>Abel,</hi> or <hi>Dauid</hi> to <hi>Abraham?</hi> Did they ſay, <hi>O Saint Abel pray for vs,</hi> or <hi>O Saint Abraham pray for vs?</hi> Did they fall downe before ſtockes and ſtones, before Idols or Images to pray or offer to them? Did they goe in pilgrimage one to anothers relickes,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:645:29"/> to doe deuotion to them? Did they intend one to performe ſatisfactions for others ſinnes? Did they pray one by the blood of another, to be brought to heauen, as by the olde <note n="c" place="margin">In feſlo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. S. Thom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Porteſſe the Papiſts prayed concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Thomas Becket,</hi> and <note n="d" place="margin">Reprooſe. pag. 109. 110.</note> Doctor <hi>Biſhop</hi> lately hath defended? A thouſand abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations there are in? Popery, whereof there is no ſhew nor ſhadow amongſt them; and yet ſhall Popery be called <hi>The old waye?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10 But let vs come nearer, and take our beginning from the time of Chriſt incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, of whom the Father gaueteſtimony from heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Matth. 17. 5.</note> 
               <hi>This is my beloued Sonne in whom I am well pleaſed, heare him;</hi> whence <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi> gathereth, that we are <note n="f" place="margin">Cyprian. l. 2. Ep. 3. <hi>Quod chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtus debeat ſolus audiri, Pater de coelo cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atur; &amp; ſi ſolus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus audundus eſt, non debemus attendere quid abquis antè nos faciendum puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerit, ſed quid qui ante omac; eſt Chriſtus prior fecerit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to heare him one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and thereof inferreth: <hi>If Chriſt onely be to be heard, we are not to regard what any before vs hath thought fit to be done, but what Christ did firſt, who is before all:</hi> thereby teaching vs to forgoe all latter cuſtomes and traditions of men, and to reſt vpon that onely which Chriſt hath taught. Now then let vs here againe thinke with our ſelues, was Chriſt a Papiſt? Did he change the olde faith of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:645:30"/> the Patriarches and Fathers to bring in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery to be the Religion, that thenceforth ſhould continue to the worlds end? Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note n="g" place="margin">Chry<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. de ſanct. &amp; ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand. ſp. <hi>Non lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutus eſt ex ſeip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſed ex Prophe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Non diſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſsit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Chriſt ſpake not of himſelfe, but out of the Law and the Prophets,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome; be ſwarued not from the Law and the Prophets.</hi> If the Religion which Chriſt taught, bee found in the Law and the Prophets, then ſurely Chriſt was no Papiſt, becauſe Popery is not found there. But for the further clearing thereof <note n="h" place="margin">Tertull de praeſcript. adu. haeret. <hi>Inprimus hoc prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>tum aliquid a Chriſto inſtitutum eſſe quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re omni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>odo deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>This I propound</hi> with <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, that there was ſome one certaine thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt, which the nations by all meanes are to beleeue.</hi> It was <hi>one</hi> onely and <hi>certaine</hi> not containing then any difference, or vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in it ſelfe, not ſubiect afterwards to any alteration or change, but ſo to be ſtill belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and practiſed as at the firſt it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. This he committed to his Apoſtles that they ſhould reach it. They did ſo, and ſo did it as that <note n="i" place="margin">Ibid. <hi>Nec ipſi qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quam ex ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrio ſuo quod <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ducer ent ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>runt, ſed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptam a Chriſto diſciplinam fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter nationibus adſignau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>runt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they made not choice of any thing at their owne will, or vpon their owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion, to bring in,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian; but the doctrine which they receiued of Chriſt, they faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully deliuered vnto the nations.</hi> And thus,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:645:30"/>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Iren. l. 3. c. 1. <hi>Euangelium primò praeco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerunt, poſtea per voluntatem Dei in ſcripturis no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis tradiderunt, fundamentum &amp; columnam ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei noſtrae futu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>they firſt preached the Goſpell,</hi> ſaith <hi>Irenaeus, and afterwards by the will of God, deliuered it vnto vs in the Scriptures, to bee the foundation and pillar of our faith. Yea and they ſo deliuered it in the Scriptures as that</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Tertull. vt ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra. <hi>Nobis non eſt opus curioſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate poſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtum, nec inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione poſt Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium; cum hoc credimus, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil deſideramus vltra credere; hoc enim prius credimus non eſſe quod vltra credere debe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>we need no curioſity after Chriſt, nor further enquiry after the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> againe: <hi>for when wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue this, we deſire to beleeue nothing further; for this we beleeue, firſt that there is nothing fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for vs to beleeue.</hi> Chriſt then taught all out of the Law and the Prophets. What Chriſt taught, he deliuered to his Apoſtles to bee preached to all Nations, and they preached it alſo, <note n="k" place="margin">Rom, 16. 26.</note> 
               <hi>by the Scriptures of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> 
               <note n="l" place="margin">Gregor. in Cant. cap. 5. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtoli à Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarum dictis fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem integram acceperunt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>receiuing the whole faith,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregory, from the ſayings of the Prophets.</hi> What the Apoſtles preached, they haue deliuered to vs in writing, and beſide that which they haue written, there is nothing further for vs to beleeue, and this is <hi>the old waye.</hi> Seeke now heere for Popery, and where is it? Looke through the Goſpels; turne ouer the Epiſtles; where is the Pope? Where is his Supremacy? where are his pardons? where is his Maſſe? where are his Images?
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:645:31"/> where is all the reſt of that filth, which like the dung out of the ſtable of <hi>Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> ſo we haue caſt out of the Church? Will they ſay of all theſe things as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſaith moſt ridiculouſly of their vowing to Saints, to giue reaſon why it is not ſpoken of in the Scriptures; <note n="m" place="margin">Bellarm. de cult. Sanct. c. 9. <hi>Cum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>rib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cript<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>cte, non <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um coeperat vſus vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>When the ſcriptures were written, the cuſtome of vowing to Saintes was not yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne?</hi> Witleſſe man, if there were no vſe or cuſtome of it then, what doe wee with it now? or what doe we with any thing elſe that Chriſt by himſelfe and his Apoſtles did not teach? <note n="n" place="margin">Ambroſ. de Virgin. lib. 3. <hi>Nos noua omnia quae Chriſtus non d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cuit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ure dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namus, &amp;c. ſi Chriſtus non do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit quod doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, etiam nos id deteſtabile iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>camus.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We iuſtly condemne all new things,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ambroſe, which Chriſt hath not taught; if Chriſt hath not taught the ſame that we teach, we iudge it worthy to be deteſted:</hi> and <note n="o" place="margin">Hieron. in Pſal. 86. <hi>Vt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptis Apoſtolis quodcu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>q aliud poſtea dic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur, abſcindatur; non habeat post<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a authoritatem. Quamuis ergò ſunctus ſit ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis poſt Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, quamuis di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertus ſit, non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>after the Apoſtles,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hierome, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhall be ſaid, is to be cut off; it is afterward of no authority, be a man holy, be he learned, after the Apoſtles he hath no authority;</hi> namely, to teach any thing further or otherwiſe then they haue taught. But this tryal the Church of Rome abhorreth, and as the theefe is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed when he is taken in his thef<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: ſo are they here confounded with ſhame, and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:645:31"/> ſtand as it were aſtoniſhed, for that they ſee the Apoſtles and Euangeliſts haue ſaid no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all for them. They would faine make ſhew of ſomething; they catch here and ſnatch there, as the dogge doth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the Riuer Nilus; but can find nothing to ſtay vpon, nothing for clearing of any cauſe that they maintaine againſt vs.</p>
            <p n="11">11 And what if we come lower to the times after the Apoſtles, ſhall we find cauſe there to take Popery for <hi>the old Religion?</hi> Of their maimed and party-communion, their Ieſuites and others confeſſe, that <note n="p" place="margin">Coſter. En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chirid. cap. 10. <hi>Diligenter no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum alterius ſpeciei commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nionem non tam Epiſcoporum mandato quàm populi vſu &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cto (conniuenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus tamen prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulihus) irrepſiſſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>it crept in by cuſtome and by the fact of the people, the Biſhops not commaunding it, but winking at it:</hi> that <note n="q" place="margin">Caſſand. Conſult. art. 22. <hi>Compertum eſt eccleſiam Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manam mille amplius à Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſto annis in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenni praeſertim &amp; ordinaria hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ſacramenti diſpenſatione, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tram<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſpeciem omnibus eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiae Chriſti mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris exhibuiſſe.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for the ſpace of a thouſand yeeres after Chriſt the Church of Rome did adminiſter ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily in both kindes;</hi> ſo as that <hi>Thomas Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi> in his time mentioneth the receiuing in one kinde, as accuſtomed but onely <note n="r" place="margin">Tho. Aquin. ſum. p. 3, q. 80. art. 12. in corp. <hi>In q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>buſdam eccleſiis obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vt populo ſanguis ſumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus non d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>in ſome Churches;</hi> and we challenge them to ſhew that euer the Communion of old time was ſo adminiſtred in any Church throughout the whole world. They cannot ſhew any ſuch thing; and ſhall we then thinke that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:645:32"/> the Religion which now commaundeth this mangling of the Sacrament of Chriſt to be <hi>the olde religion?</hi> Of tranſubſtantiati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Scotus</hi> one of their great ſchoolemen ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgeth, that <note n="ſ" place="margin">Bellarm. de ſacram. Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt. lib. 3. c. 23. <hi>Scotus ait, ante Lateranenſe concilium non ſuiſſe dogma ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dei tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiationem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>before the Councel of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran,</hi> almoſt twelue hundred yeares after Chriſt, <hi>it was no Article of Faith:</hi> and of their other tricks and deuices for the vpholding thereof, <hi>of accidents ſubſiſting without any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect, and giuing nouriſhment and food to the body,</hi> and ſuch like, the authors of their firſt <hi>Index Expurgatorius,</hi> plainely ſay, that <note n="t" place="margin">Index Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgat. Belg. in Bertram. <hi>Quae ſubtiliſsime &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riſsime poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior aetas per ſp. ſanctum addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>latter time added them by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> If latter time haue added th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe things, then ſurely theſe things are no part of <hi>the old waye.</hi> And wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as they pretend the holy Ghoſt as the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor hereof, we will returne to them that which <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith to the hereticke, <note n="u" place="margin">Chryſoſt. de ſanct adorand. ſp. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bi legiſti haec: Ex quo non legit haec ſcripta ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ex ſeipſo lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>itur, manif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtu e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t quod non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet ſp. ſanctum,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Where haſt thou read this? Becauſe he readeth not theſe things in the ſcriptures, but ſpeaketh of himſelfe, it is manifeſt that hee hath not the holy Ghost.</hi> To let paſſe their ſeuen ſacraments mentioned before, their Popes pardons, their Iubilees, their Church-treaſury, their worſhipping of Images, with ſundry other
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:645:32"/> apparant and manifeſt nouelties, doe they find in <hi>the old religion</hi> thoſe preceps which they now deliuer of deluding magiſtrates in their examinations, by Equiuocations and mentall reſeruations, and Euaſions? Was it thought lawfull by that religion that a man might take a ſolemne oath, and then play mock-holiday therewith, and ſalue by the thought of the mind, the falſe anſwere of the tongue? <hi>Iuſtinus Martyr</hi> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs the practiſe of <hi>the old waye,</hi> farre dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from this Popiſh way, <note n="x" place="margin">Iuſtin. Mart. Apolog. <hi>Emori malumus prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter confeſsionem fidei quam aut mentiri aut in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſitores fallere: alioqui in promptu erat vſurpare vulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum illud: Iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta lingua eſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimus iniuratus eſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>We had ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther die for the confeſsion of our faith, then ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther lie or beguile them that doe examine vs; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe we might readily take vp the common ſaying: My tongue is ſworne, my minde is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne.</hi> That which they would not take vp, is now taken vp by Ieſuites and Papiſts, and that is deemed lawful and right which euen the very light of nature taught men to condemne as wicked &amp; vnlawfull. In a word, where doe they finde in <hi>the old waye</hi> that which before I mentioned, that the Pope or Biſhop of Rome, hath a ſuperio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ouer Emperours, and Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces?
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:645:33"/> that he hath authority to depoſe them from their crownes and dignities, and to releaſe their ſubiects of the allegeance which they haue ſworne vnto them? that vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his excommunication, it is lawfull for their ſubiects to rebell againſt them, and to practiſe all hoſtility for the remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of them? O moſt impudent &amp; ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men, carried now beyonde all bounds of modeſty or honeſty, who haue written ſo many bookes of la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e for the defence of this paradoxe? when as in all their bookes they doe not, they cannot bring one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or ſillable of antiquity, no precept, no example for iuſt fication thereof, which notwithſtanding they commend for <note n="y" place="margin">Bellarm e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. ad Archi. presb. <hi>Vnum ex praecipius fidei noſtrae capitibus &amp; rel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ntis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>a chiefe and ſpeciall point of the Catholicke and Chriſtian faith.</hi> But this point of Chriſtian faith <hi>Tertullian</hi> knew not, when hee affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the name and behalfe of chriſtians, that they held <note n="z" place="margin">Tertul. aduer. Scapul. <hi>Colimus imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ratorem vt hominem a Deo ſecundum, ſolo De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> minorem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Emperour to be a man next vnto God, and inferiour to God onely:</hi> that <note n="a" place="margin">Idem. Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get. cap. 30. <hi>In cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us ſolius pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate ſunt: à quo ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cundi, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt quem primi ante omnes.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Emperours were vnder the power of God onely, being next vnto God, and after God the firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men.</hi> Nor <hi>Optatus,</hi> who ſayeth that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:645:33"/> aboue <note n="b" place="margin">Optat. lib. 3. <hi>Super imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem non eſt niſi ſolus Deus qui fecit imperato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the Emperour, there is none but God onely that made the Emperour.</hi> Nor <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> who ſaith of the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius;</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">Chryſoſt. ad pop. Antioch. hom. 2. <hi>Laeſus eſt qui non habet parem vlliom ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per terram: ſummitas &amp; ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>put omnium ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per terram ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>He hath no peere vpon earth: hee is the head and higheſt top of all men vpon the earth.</hi> Nor <hi>Cyril,</hi> who ſaith to the ſame Emperour <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoſius,</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cyril. Epiſt. ad Theodoſ. praefixa lib. aduer. Iulian. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtrae ſerenita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti nullus ſtatus aequalis eſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>There is no ſtate equall to your Maieſty;</hi> 
               <note n="e" place="margin">Idem de rect. fide ad Theod. <hi>Vos eſtis &amp; ſummarum dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitatum ſontes &amp; ſupra om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eminenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>you are the fountaine of the higheſt dignities and aboue all eminency of men.</hi> Nor <hi>Gregory</hi> Biſhop of Rome, who acknowledgeth to <hi>Maurici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> the Emperour, that <note n="f" place="margin">Gregor lib. 2. Epiſt. 61. <hi>Pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas ſuper omnes hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nes domino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum meorum pietati coelitùs data.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>to him was giuen pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er from heauen ouer all men.</hi> Nor <hi>Agapetus</hi> a Deacon of Conſtantinople, who ſaide to <hi>Iuſtinian</hi> the Emperour; <note n="g" place="margin">Agapet, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raen. ad Iuſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. cap. 21. <hi>Non habet Rex in terris ſe quenquan altiorem.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The King hath none Superiour to him vpon earth.</hi> VVhich ſentence <note n="h" place="margin">Anton. Meliſſ. lib. 2. cap. 1</note> 
               <hi>Antony</hi> the Abbot, ſurnamed <hi>Magnus,</hi> tranſcribed into his Sermons as Catholick and ſound: as did alſo <note n="i" place="margin">Maxim. ſentent. ſer. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Maximus an ancient Monke,</hi> but now the <note n="k" place="margin">Index Expurgat. Hiſp. in Biblioth. ſanct. Patrum. tom. 1. <hi>Dele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur illa verba: Non enim habet in terris ſe quicquam excelſius.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Index Expurgatorius</hi> of Spaine hath condemned this ſentence as vncatholicke, and vnſound; and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the ſame in the ſermons of <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> to bee henceforth omitted and left out.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:645:34"/> But what? ſhall we thinke that all theſe were ignorant of the Catholicke faith? was the Biſhop of Rome then the higheſt State vpon earth, and did not they vnderſtand ſo much? And if it were ſo, was there neuer a <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> neuer a <hi>Matthaeus Tortus,</hi> neuer a <hi>ſerpens tortuoſus</hi> that would hiſſe and thruſt out the ſting, againſt theſe impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of ſo maine a a point of Chriſtian be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe? Or ſhall we not rather thinke theſe moſt ſhameleſſe and vngodly creatures that will thus willfully goe againſt ſo cleare a ſtreame of antiquity; hauing nothing, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all from thence to alleadge for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of that they ſay; nothing for any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour thereof, but only that they bring ſome ſpeeches, touching generally the dignity of Prieſthood, whereby they may as well prooue euery hedge-prieſt to be ſuperiour to the greateſt Monarch in the world, and the meaneſt Biſhop in the world, to bee e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall to the Pope? Thus whileſt they ſtill pretend and make ſhew of <hi>the old waye,</hi> they giue vs iuſt occaſion, to ſay of them as <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian</hi> ſaid of the old Romaness; <note n="l" place="margin">Tertull. Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loget. c. 6. <hi>Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>datis ſemper an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitatem &amp; nouè de die vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ye are ſtill
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:645:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> commending of antiquity, and are full of new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uices from day to day.</hi> But wee take know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge hereby of that Antichriſt, of whom it was foretold by the Apoſtle that he ſhould <note n="m" place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2. 4.</note> 
               <hi>exalt himſelfe aboue all that is called God, or that is worſhipped:</hi> which Saint <hi>Hierome</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poundeth to conſiſt in this, that <note n="n" place="margin">Hieron. in Dan. c. 7. <hi>Eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſupra omne quod dicitur De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, cunctam reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionem ſuae ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ijciens poteſtati.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>he ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect all Religion to his owne power;</hi> hee ſhall make of Religion what he liſt, euen as the Pope doth.</p>
            <p n="12">12 It remaineth now briefely to note what in duty concerneth vs when God hath made his way knowne vnto vs, and that is, <hi>to walke therein.</hi> For as it booteth not to know the precepts of bodily health, if we put not in practiſe what we know; ſo nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther auaileth it to know the way of eternal life, if we onely know it, and be careleſſe to walke accordingly. To walke, I ſay, both by preſeruing integrity of faith, and by yeelding conuerſation of life correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and agreeable to our faith<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> becauſe the way doth not onely teach vs true faith, but alſo a vertuous and godly life. Here it is for vs to learne wiſdome. If to know the
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:645:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> way were ſufficient to eternall life, how many would obtaine ſaluation, who now goe headlong to deſtruction? To beholde the kingdome of God a farre off, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the land of Canaan, whoſe heart doth it no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> moue and enamor with the deſire of it? in whom doth it not breed a wil to know the way to come vnto it? But to walke in this way and to continue therin, to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe the yoke of Chriſt, to deny our ſelues and to mortifie the deſires of the fleſh, and of the world; to fight againſt ſinne that fighteth againſt vs, &amp; in a word to follow the example of Ieſus Chriſt, and as we haue receiued him ſo to walke in him; theſe are things ſo vncouch, ſo ſtrange and croſſe to our nature and will, as that many rather then they will thus doe, doe fruſtrate all their knowledge, and are content to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray their owne ſaluation. <note n="o" place="margin">Bernard. in Cant. ſer. 21. <hi>Quàm pauci poſt te, ô Domine Ieſu ire volunt, cùm tamen ad te peruenire n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mo ſit qui nolit, ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entibus cunctis quia in dextera tua delectatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes vſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> in finem, &amp;c. Ex his erat ille qui dicebat, Moriatur ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma mea morte iuſtorum, &amp;c. Mortem ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alium optant ſibi etiam carnales, quorum tamen vitam abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ſcientes pretioſam mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem eſſe ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>How few are there, O Lord Ieſus, that will follow thee, ſaith</hi> Bernard, <hi>whereas there is no man but is deſirous to come vnto thee, all men knowing that at thy right hand there are pleaſures for euermore? Such a one was</hi> Balaam, <hi>ſaith he, who ſaide, Let my
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:645:35" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſoule dye the death of the righteous, and let my latter end be like vnto his.</hi> And thus <hi>carnall men deſire to themſelues the death of them that are ſpirituall, becauſe they know that precious in the ſight of the Lord is the death of his Saints; but in the meane time, they abhorre and ſhunne their kind of life.</hi> How many are there, that can like well to yeeld vnto God all externall acts of deuotion, but ſo that he will giue them the liberty of their inward affections? How many can bee content to admit the faith of Chriſt, ſo that they may be requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red no workes, or at leaſt no other workes then they pleaſe themſelues? How many are glad to embrace Chriſt as Ieſus to ſaue them, who like not to haue him vrged vpon them as their Lord to gouerne them? But Chriſt cannot in any wiſe brooke this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membring of himſelfe. The true mother could not endure to heare of the deuiding of her child. If Chriſt be truly conceiued &amp; borne in vs, we cannot yeeld to that deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, of him but wil receiue him whole. If we will needs deuide our ſelues, to God by profeſsion, to the Diuell by action; to
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:645:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> Chriſt by faith, to our ſelues<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſurely God becauſe he cannot bee content with halfe, will leaue the diuell to take all. Let vs not be like the Philiſtines, who <note n="p" place="margin">1. Sam. 5. 2.</note> tooke the arke of God, and ſet it vp by <hi>Dagon</hi> their idoll God. <note n="q" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 77. <hi>Qui ſic ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Dei vt veter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> vanitate non ſe exuant, ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miles ſunt hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus populi eius, qui captiuatam arcam teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti iuxta ſua idola poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erunt,</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>So doe they,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auſtin, who ſo receiue the Teſtament of God, as that they ſtrip not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of their former vanity.</hi> So doe they that take the faith of Chriſt, and ſet it with the idols of their owne corrupt and ſinful luſts. Let vs not be like the Iewes <note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 27. 34. Vulg.</note> who gaue VVine indeed to Chriſt but mingled with Gall. <note n="ſ" place="margin">Origen. in Mat. tract. 35. <hi>Quanticun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam quidem oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticam ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem male, dant e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> viru <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> bibere f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lle permix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>So do they,</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen, who are minded rightly according to the doctrine of the Church, but doe liue amiſſe.</hi> Let vs not be like <note n="t" place="margin">Matth. 21. 19.</note> the Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree in the Goſpell, which had leaues onely and no fruite; that tree we know was curſed by our Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iour Chriſt, and withered ſoone way. This befel not for the trees ſake, but in the tree Chriſt would teach vs what we are to expect, if we yeeld leaues without fruit, if we haue ſhadow and ſhew onely with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtance; if we labour onely to know the way, and make no conſcience to walke in it. <note n="u" place="margin">Luk. 12. 47.</note> 
               <hi>The ſeruant that knoweth his maſters wil,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:645:36"/> and doeth it not, ſhal be beaten with many ſtripes;</hi> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Iam. 4. 17.</note> and <hi>he that knoweth what is good, and doth it not, to him it is ſinne.</hi> God direct vs the right way to come vnto him, that by vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding we may know him: and by obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, may ſerue him, and may ſo paſſe the courſe of this tranſitory life, as that the end therof may be to reſt with him in euerlaſting peace and bliſſe, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and only Sauiour Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Page 5. line 7. for in ſinne, read by ſinne. p. 19. l. 9. for not theſe veſſels but theſe. r.</hi> not, <hi>thoſe veſſels,</hi> but, <hi>theſe. p. 41. l. 18. for ſeducements and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retickes. r. ſeducements of Hereticks. p. 26. l. 11. for like credit. r little credit. p. 29. l. 2. for deuiſe. r. aduiſe. p. 26. l. 8. for party. Neſtorian. r. party-Neſtorian. Ibid. l 21. for yet, r. yea.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
